First, we consider the air conditioning requirements of a data center
servers and other equipment generate a lot
of heat which must be handled appropriately.
This is not just to make it comfortable when humans are present
but to ensure the equipment is kept within its operating parameters.
When equipment gets too hot, it can lead to quicker failure or avoided warranty.
Most equipment is programmed to automatically shut down
when a certain temperature threshold is met.
This helps to protect the equipment but a system that
is shut down is not available to the users.
An abnormal system shutdown can also lead to the loss or corruption of data.
Another consideration for the on premises
data center is the fire suppression systems
in the United States.
Most commercial buildings are required to have sprinkler
systems that are activated in a fire.
These sprinklers minimize the amount of damage caused to the
building and keep the fire from spreading to adjacent areas,
but they can be detrimental to electronic
equipment as water and electricity don't mix
while most water based fire suppression systems don't
work like they do in the movies where
a fire in one part of the building turns on the sprinklers for the entire building.
Another hazard is having water overhead in a data center.
Eventually water pipes will fail and may leak on equipment.
This risk can be reduced somewhat by using a dry pipe system
that keeps the water out of the pipes over the data center.
These systems have a valve outside the data center that is
only opened when a sensor indicates a fire is present.
Since water is not held in the pipes above the data center,
the risk of leaks is reduced.